welcome to episode number 46 today on
the show we have Daniel schmuck tan
Berger again this time he's talking
about existential risks and how to avoid
them we've already done several other
episodes with Danielle before and they
were always some of our favorites a very
mind-expanding and inspirational but I
think this one is particularly important
because he talks about some of the most
pressing issues that we face on our
planet today and proposes some ways that
we can solve them if you want to check
out the previous episodes that we've
done with Danielle go to future thinkers
that org slash Daniel to get all the
books resources and the other things
that we mentioned in this episode go to
future thinkers that work slash 46 this
episode is brought to you by BCD see
they're working on several blockchain
based apps to help save the environment
one of them is called eco chain and it's
a crowdfunding and investment platform
for renewable energy projects where
people can invest in new clean energy
installations and get an ROI so BCDC is
doing a token sale which is now
happening in November 2017 but the
presale is already happening now you can
see our report and listen to the
interview we did with them by going to
future thinkers org slash BC DC you can
also find all the links to their website
white paper and bounty campaign there as
well last but not least before we get in
the episode we want to thank our recent
patrons ray and Dean for supporting us
on patreon all right let's get started
welcome to future thinkers org a podcast
about the evolution of technology
society and consciousness I'm Mike
Gilliland and I'm UV Ivanova to get
notified of new podcasts and videos go
to future thinkers org and subscribe to
our mailing list you can also find us on
iTunes stitcher and you tube if you like
what we do and you want to help us make
more podcasts and videos give us a like
or review share it with your friends and
consider becoming a patron go to
patreon.com/crashcourse in reorg
slash app last but not least if you want
to get access to more content hidden
episodes or if you just want to chat
with us in previous guests then check
out our community at community our
future thinkers org Daniel welcome to
the show it's good to have you on again
so today we're talking about existential
risks which is a topic I know you're
quite familiar with that you know you've
brought up in past episodes with us so
this is something I've actually really
been looking forward to getting into
with you great so why don't we start
with the big questions what are some of
the biggest existential risks that we
are facing on the planet right now so
for those who aren't familiar the term
existential risk means some risk that
could stop us from existing so a species
threatening event there's also plenty of
catastrophic risks that would just
really suck even though we wouldn't be
completely wiped out as a species so
their versions of World War three that
are existential kinds of nuclear
holocaust that nobody makes it through
there are kinds of World War three that
are catastrophic meaning some group of
people in remote areas make it through
but the atmosphere holds you rhenium and
you know most of the people did very
poorly so we're kind of interested in
preventing all of those things right so
what are the categories first there's
different ways of kind of chunking and
different ways of doing taxonomy one
thing we can look at is start by saying
there are kind of human-induced things
and then there's kind of natural
phenomena the natural phenomena are
things that either
arise from within our Earth and
biosphere or outside of it so outside of
it is things like solar flares and
Carrington events asteroids that can be
catastrophic or existential and
obviously
you know within our atmosphere most of
the natural phenomena that would occur
would not be existential but there are
some super caldera kinds of scenarios
that would be we're obviously interested
in any of them because you know if if
there was an event that we just couldn't
avoid here then Mars colony moves up on
the priority list right mm-hmm but
surprisingly most of these things if we
have more Intel about them many of them
can be avoided or at least mitigated
against so for instance if we look at
something like a Carrington event we're
looking at solar flares or coronal mass
ejections that besides the just effect
that they would have on biology directly
would also have effects on electrical
circuitry as far as biology goes there
might be a impact on one part of the
planet people can go underground it's
not that big a deal but as far as frying
the circuitry goes if we're talking
about frying the circuitry of nuclear
cooling stations on the power plant so
then they turn into nuclear volcanoes
that's a pretty big deal now we could of
course do things to mitigate against the
sensitivity there like hardening the
nuclear cooling stations and you know
other forms of key infrastructure so
even with regard to things that we can
call natural phenomena obviously you
know there are projects that are looking
at asteroids and other near-earth
objects because depending upon what we
see they might actually be movable and
there are a number of projects focused
on that then we move our attention to
you know human induced things and we can
look at the ones that go through
environmental pathways basically we
either through biodiversity loss or
climate change ocean acidification or
other kinds of effects on our biosphere
we create a biosphere that is
uninhabitable to humans but we don't
even have to get to full uninhabitable
'ti for partial uninhabitable 'ti to
lead to the beginning of cascade effects
you know when we look at what happened
in Syria we see did a major part of what
happened in factoring there were many
many factors simultaneously but one part
of it was droughts in an area that had
not had droughts led to subsistence
farmers moving into the cities the tax
to the resource capacity of those cities
beyond their limits that led to resource
Wars that led
two factions and that whole kind of
thing so when we start looking at
climate change creating massive numbers
of refugees and the refugee dynamics
leading to war dynamics and resource
shortage wars economic collapse and then
you know cascading Wars you can have
scenarios where environmental phenomena
are the first step in a series of
cascades that can occur so you've got
all of the environmental phenomenon the
effects of on coral of ocean temperature
ocean acidification the loss of big fish
in the trophic cascades key species
collapse throughout many different
dynamics pollinators like there's a lot
there's a lot of things in there then we
can look at other reasons for just human
induced violence towards each other so
all of the reasons that something like a
world war and we see right now
the United States leaving its position
of clear supremacy as a superpower we
see China moving up into that position
we have rarely seen transitions of power
go smoothly in the history of
civilization and we've never had
transitions of power be at this kind of
global level and with existential level
technologies and with over 7 billion
people and with a biosphere near
collapse and near fragility points like
we're in a very different place but even
when just there was a local hegemony
where the power was moving from one kind
of local power to another those were
usually not easy transition so lots of
different scenarios and then there are
the exponential tech scenarios where
different kinds of exponential
technology exponential technology means
exponentially increased power to affect
stuff and whether we're talking about
through AI or through CRISPR and biotech
or through nanotech you know or through
robotics if we have exponentially
increasing ability to affect stuff
without exponentially increasing good
choice making that is just self
terminating no matter what and that is
the scenario we have right now so
exponential tech can lead to existential
scenarios on purpose or on accident
right you can have just much more
powerful kind of capacities military
capacities and much more powerful
capacities that even smaller actor
are able to get nuclear bomb started off
as such a difficult thing that only huge
state actors could have it those state
actors could watch each other you could
have a mutually assured destruction
systems and nobody could use it but as
you start to have exponential tech that
becomes distributed where smaller and
smaller actors have access to larger and
larger potential to affect things the
ability to avoid that happening gets
harder and harder and then you also have
exponential tech that leads to
existential scenarios accidentally so
most of the AI risks that boström lays
out in super intelligence the gray goo
risks that Drexler lays out you know
these are mostly where we create in
autopoietic system we create a self
fueling system that has a faster
feedback loop is more adaptive than
biology and not commensurate with
biology and so we have to avoid
accidental extinction as well as on
purpose extinction you know that's kind
of a rough lay of the land of the
categories of existential risk now if we
take a step back from it we can say all
of these categories have some things in
common some deeper underlying drivers
that are actually the real existential
concerns because if at this level the
scenarios are basically countless but if
we go deeper one way of saying it is
that the real existential risk is a loss
of sense making loss of the ability to
actually make sense of the world around
us and what is worth doing what the
likely effects of things will be what
the effects of our actions are now and
so let me think about it how long do we
have with ocean acidification before the
coral die right now the thoughts on that
vary so widely that it's either the most
important issue or we have quite a bit
of time and is Fukushima really close to
releasing a lot of radiation or not and
can North Korea's nuke SRIA Lee reached
certain places or not and what are the
real risks with AGI parasitic AI
etcetera like if we don't have better
ability to make sense of these things
then they just all fail scenarios right
because we don't know how to prioritize
what should actually get attention paid
to it and what could be successful and
what's not likely to be successful so we
can say that a lack of in
information coherence is one of the
things that is at the heart of driving
them and now to take us deeper step we
say well within capitalism and we can
set them further back in a moment but
let's take that step within capitalism
where we're playing a competitive game
we're playing a win-lose game usually
zero-sum sometimes small positive some
but still fundamentally win lose
information is a source of competitive
advantage so we are incented to both
hoard information and to create
disinformation we actually like if we
succeed at that we will actually do
better within the system so as you have
exponential technologies the ability to
do more media spread more different info
through more channels etc how do we have
exponential information tech with the
incentive to disinformation and actually
be able to have enough coherent
information to have any idea what the
is going on well basically we don't
you know when you think about like
getting towards the tipping point of
climate change where if we you know we
get to a positive feedback loop with
warming or something and if we don't
stop a dynamic before a certain point we
won't be able to afterwards we're
actually pretty close to the point of
peak disk coherence where if we get to
that place we might not actually be able
to recover coherence and so I would say
that's one way of thinking about what is
actually essential another way of theme
about what's essential is like we said
exponential technology it's very hard
for people's intuition to grasp what an
exponential curve is because most of the
things we experience don't feel like
exponential things but most of
technology that is exponential is
increasing our ability to affect
something with our choice but it's not
increasing the quality of our choice now
when you multiply these together
actually decreased information coherency
with increased impact that is a self
terminating scenario right so what are
some of the ways of avoiding that
especially I liked what you said about
our loss of sense making and the
exponential curve of that also it's a
really interesting factor that I think a
lot of people aren't talking about it
relates to one of the questions I was
going to ask what do we do about
the sort of institutionalized ignorance
of people to what is actually going on
and there's you mentioned the corporate
interests and producing disinformation
but there's also you know bad
educational systems that are outdated or
motivated by different factors that have
nothing to do with actually giving
people good information and then there
is research that serves corporate needs
and then there's media propaganda and
politics and all the stuff so what kind
of tools do we actually have to change
these systems in a way that they serve
the planet rather than serving these
individual interests we could say well
when you talk about sense making
shouldn't that be science shouldn't
science be sense making in the same way
that we shouldn't journalism be sense
making ray aren't these shouldn't the
intelligence agencies of the world be
sense-making you know we've seen
scenarios where a scientist publishes a
scientific paper in a prestigious
scientific journal where the paper that
they wrote is complete gibberish they
made it up the technical sounding words
but it's actually gibberish and it goes
through the publication process because
they came from the right university or
whatever and they were doing that just
to show that the peer review process is
broken we've also seen where you know
stats like 50% of the articles posted in
places like Journal of American Medical
Association five years later the
findings are found to have been
misinterpreted or wrong or had bad
methodology etc 50% wrong means that if
I'm reading a cutting-edge medical
journal my chances of knowing what's
true are 50/50 right it's like pulling
teeth Yves would give me as much of a
sense of what's true it's unbelievable
yeah is a broken sense making system
within science if you want to think
about what the heart of science is like
what the essence of the philosophy of
Sciences the essence of it is earnest
inquiry right like earnest desire to
understand the nature of reality and so
whatever the speed of sound actually is
I don't care if it is different than I
think it is I want to find out there's a
certain reverence for reality and
respect for the nature of what is beyond
my own ideas about it or how I can
benefit from it that is at the heart of
the scientific impulse
but the scientists that need paid and
the equipment has to come from somewhere
and if there are some of the answers
that are more profitable than other
answers then it's easier to put money
into it because I'll be able to get that
money back and if an herb or a plant has
some medicinal property but I will never
be able to patent it and I won't be able
to recoup the money that I get from you
know the small margins that I would put
into the research how can we afford to
pay for it but we will with say
something synthetic thing I can get a
patent on and etc right so what actually
gets researched within that structure
and how it gets researched so you have
you have to factor how deep those kind
of perverse incentives end up trickling
through the whole thing so then you ask
a good question which is within a system
within a fundamentally win-lose
game-theoretic system how do you prevent
these issues and be able to have real
coherency when we are incented to
withhold information and even you know
like you'll you'll see in soccer
football whatever someone will fake left
to try and get the other person to go
left and then they'll actually go right
right like that's disinformation
intentional disinformation so that you
can throw the opponent off so you can
win this is not different in
corporations or Nations right and Intel
and counter Intel and an intentional
dissing firm ation same thing but with
global level consequence so here's
another good way of thinking about it
think about early tribes as competitive
teams almost like a sports team where
they have to work really well together
and be very coherent with each other to
be able to compete with other teams and
military conflicts when they occur and
compete with the other teams for scarce
resources in the shared environment the
shared commons say they they weren't
military right they're just doing their
own thing there's plenty of abundance
but then if any of them realize that
they can do this military thing go kill
another tribe take their stuff and get
the riverfront that they had or get
whatever kinds of things they had
acquired and developed that actually
worked for them work better now everyone
else has to build defensive militaries
at least otherwise they lose by default
and so one of the things to get in the
history of win lose game theory is that
one
it worked you could actually go kill the
other people take their stuff and make
stuff better for you and you know your
people and - if you didn't play win lose
game theory and someone else did you
lost by default right which is why most
of the more peaceable less militaristic
cultures got wiped out so then we say
you know one of the tribes is just
bigger and stronger than us we're not
going to be able to compete with them
but if two or three of us smaller tribes
band together we can but then of course
the other side has to compete so they
band together and so now we move from
tribes to villages right and then we can
move up to kingdoms and to nation-states
and to global economic trading bloc's I
mean think about those evolutions of
what we think of as like civilization
structures as evolutions of competitive
teams within a win-lose game theoretic
structure that have more and more power
to be able to out-compete the other one
and that's both have more people that
can be coherent with each other against
the other one right so then where as a
nation where a team competing against
the other one we have a shared
military-industrial complex paid for by
taxes whatever or as a religion or a
race so we can have some overlapping
teams but once you get to the point
where all of the teams are stepping up
simultaneously that's the kind of
evolutionary driver they're stepping up
in their power once you get to the point
that you have exponential technological
power on multiple teams where the amount
of power that it would take to actually
win would require destroying the playing
field which becomes inevitable right
inevitably power will keep increasing
until it's actually bigger than the
playing field can tolerate and then
winning pretty much means losing because
there is nothing left to win right so
right now we're at a place where the
superpowers of the world cannot win a
war against each other when you have
hundreds of times the nuclear capacity
necessary to kill all life on Earth
there is no winnable war but we keep
building more military capacity
we just spend you know a trillion and a
half dollars on the f-35 because we
didn't have badass enough jets with the
military that already has all the
technical capability that it has in the
u.s. right and and think about what a
trillion and a half dollars of resources
means to other kinds of things and so
when you say why did we ever get more
than five times as many nukes as we
needed to kill all life on Earth like
after you've got enough nukes to kill
life on Earth I
ten times why do you keep building more
- well you have hundreds of times was
that ever a really just strategically
smart idea or was that because we had a
for-profit military-industrial complex
that makes money when that happens where
the people who are in positions of
decision-making power also happen to be
shareholders or have vested interest in
those structures and this is not blaming
the people involved these are structural
right these are structural dynamics and
so can you have lasting peace and a
for-profit military-industrial complex
at the same time of course not right
like that's supplied and demand 101 that
if there is a massive capacity for
supply it has to protect the demand and
then you think about where those
perverse incentives go everywhere right
health care where if people weren't sick
then the system loses all of its
resource and so how could it ever really
invest in prevention deeply when its
profitability depends upon symptom
management if you even cured people
quickly that's not profitable but if you
manage symptoms ongoingly its profitable
and if the symptom management causes
other issues that need more symptom
management ie more meds that's just like
an upsell or cross-sell maximizing the
lifetime revenue of a customer that
happens to be a patient so when you
think about you know win lose game
theory within that kind of incentive
structure where we can't win at the wars
anymore and yet we're moving closer to
the kinds of tensions where war becomes
more and more probable and we also can't
win at competing for extracting the
scarce resource when we've already
extracted so much scarce resource we're
almost at the biospheres limits right
we're almost at the limits of what can
be handled in the extraction of oil or
fish or grazing land for cattle or so
many things and so either we continue
with win lose game theory and it becomes
Omni lose-lose catastrophic ly or we
have to figure out how to have that
power not turned against the other power
and figure out what does Omni win-win
mean where no one has incentives that
are misaligned with the well-being of
others in that system that has that much
power and that's really the fork in the
road we're at as a species for the first
time ever now is
either figure out what on me win-win
means economically as a worldview
governance wise we either figure out
what that means or we continue with
win-lose and it becomes olney lose-lose
which pretty much means we either step
up into a radically higher level of
quality of life existence but the new
kind of collective intelligence or we
have a catastrophic step down
existential or near existential but like
in the next not very long time that's
really the fork in the road and what
evidence do you see of us going down one
path or the other with more preference
if we just plot curves it doesn't look
good right if we just plot the curves of
what has happened so far with regard to
how much harm came from new power that
we developed and we look at how fast we
are developing new power on exponential
curves if we look at the population
curves and we look at you know biosphere
issues like it it all looks pretty bad
from that point of view and you can try
and take the technology mister out and
say but look at the rate at which we are
developing solutions but here's the
problem with that here's another way of
thinking about what the driver of the
existential risk and all the
catastrophic risks are so one way is of
thinking about it is that when lose game
theory is driving the whole thing right
when lose structures are driving the
whole thing with win lose game theory
multiplied by exponential power and
exponential populations another way of
looking at it is a lack of information
coherence I mean there's information
coherence and coherence as beings and
agents with each other another way of
thinking about it is a lack of coherence
around value measures and this is
actually a very deep and essential way
of thinking about it think about a tree
in an ecosystem and we say well what is
the value of that tree
well it's providing a home for a bunch
of pollinators and birds it's providing
food for them with flowers it's
stabilizing topsoil it's symbiotic with
the micro rui-zi and the fungus and
bacteria in the soil it's providing
shade for all of these things it's you
know pulling out co2 and producing
oxygen and providing food for animals
and you know it might have millions of
value metrics as part of this kind of
complex ecosystem but
we cut it down to make it $10,000 with
the two-by-fours and its value is
$10,000 and the two by fours right like
they're not sequestering co2 and
stabilizing topsoil they are serving as
a structural strut it's this one really
simple thing right structural stress so
we took this very complex thing and we
reduced the complexity of it radically
we made it a very simple thing so we
down cycled the out of it because
what the metric we were seeking to
optimize was dollars in my account and
so like a dollar is a value metric but I
get the $10,000 from that tree or I get
$10,000 from the elephant tusks right or
I get 10,000 from this servicer well as
I count how do I relate the value of an
elephant tusks or a person's art or a
tree like these should not be fungible
they should not be inter exchangeable
these are fundamentally different things
but because I remove all of the
information from them in all of the
contexts I want them to be simply
exchangeable in terms of capital so I
can maximize the ease of transaction to
grow pools of capital that is an
extinction area dynamic is that we're
taking complex value and turning it into
simple value that almost sounds like a
gray goo scenario of itself it is we're
taking all of these super complex things
and reducing them to this homogenous goo
that is monetary value I actually just
saw a really good article that was
called capitalism as a paper clip
Maximizer and it's actually a really fun
thought experiment paper clip Maximizer
if the people aren't familiar was I
don't remember who came up with it first
but it was in Nick Bostrom's book on AI
issues and just said you know we could
have an AI whose job was you know
working at a paperclip company to
maximize paperclip production and it
also had the capacity to upgrade its own
capacity and it ends up getting into a
place where it makes all these paper
clips and upgrades its own ability to
make more paper clips and then it starts
competing you know taking all of the
resource that humans needed to make
paper clips because that's its algorithm
and as its increasing its own capacity
it's being able to out-compete us and
then it realizes that we're made of
atoms that it can make paperclips out of
it
you know that it's this kind of
continuously growing right this
autopoietic capacity that's just turning
everything into paperclips and so who
they were saying you know this paper of
capitalism is a paperclip Maximizer
because capital is making more capital
that's kind of the gist of this
distributed system rather than as a
central AI it's this distributed kind of
collective intelligence system it uses
these distributed human bio processors
within it but because we've reduced the
value to capital and having more capital
makes it easier to get more capital the
capital gains interest faster than the
overall economy grows gives you access
to more financial services etc then you
know that's the goal so to say
capitalism as a paperclip Maximizer is a
a reasonable thing and Drexler's model
of gray goo was based on another
exponential tech which was nanotech the
ability to rearrange things at a
molecular or atomic level if we do that
right it's pretty awesome right if we do
it right it's like the replicator from
Star Trek we can take trash and turn it
back into rad stuff at the level of just
atoms and that actually might be the
future of the materials economy is that
we have quantum computing that has
enough sophistication you know give or
take a million qubits to be able to
properly direct nano Tronics to take old
stuff and turn it back into new stuff at
an atomic level creating a closed-loop
materials economy that can upcycle
indefinitely but if we get it wrong then
you can have you know these machines
that are just turning everything into
gooks or Drexler had this you know
models called gray goo and in a way UV
you're right capitalism as gray goo is
you know we take this tree with this
radical contextualized complex value and
take it out of its context and give it
this reduced abstracted simplified value
metric and we've done that to 80% of the
old-growth forests that the earth spent
billions of years developing you know
and 90% of the large fish species in the
ocean and then what is that capital
really do other than continue to do that
autopoietic thing and so when people
think about like what is capitalism and
honestly like we can say communism and
socialism were really actually subsets
of this kind of resource concentration
system it's a process of abstracting
value so we go from call
flex value to abstracted value and then
extracting it and accumulating it that
particular model came from colleague
Forrest Landry and no capitalism does
that but socialism and communism have
other versions of doing that but that's
the core thing that's the ring of power
that has to be broken is abstraction of
value and specifically a reductive
abstraction extraction so you remove the
content from its context and
accumulation and that's how you take a
complex system that is resilient and
turn it into a complicated system that's
not resilient that becoming
progressively simpler in kill it this
brings up something I find to be
fascinating which is the use of
blockchain to tokenize abstract value do
you have thoughts about this and whether
it's actually possible to do this I can
get more specific if you need yeah
please do so we had an interview last
year with Vince means and he talked
about tokenizing these abstract values
actually he used the tree example so
what if you can tokenize all the the
extra abstract value that a tree
provides you know have a token for
oxygen converted that sort of thing
and what if you can optimize those
different tokens in the same way that
capitalism optimizes capital can we use
these other systems of value and use
them as currency as well I say that
loosely and optimize that using the
existing capitalist system I don't think
so lazy faire capitalism always kind of
goes there it says the tragedy of the
Commons is because if nobody owns it
then they'll it up but if someone
owned it they'd take responsibility for
it so really the answer is to have
everyone own everything every coral reef
every everything is owned and we have
some way of creating capitalists value
in the process of owning it this breaks
down for a number of reasons so why is a
are not worth anything in gold is worth
so much because in a win-lose game model
something that everyone has access to
and can't not have access to and I can't
get anymore of doesn't give me
competitive advantage so everyone has
access to air so I don't need to value
it I don't need to pay attention to it
and now if I cut down this tree of
course I'm cutting down something that
produces oxygen and sequester co2 but
I'm not cutting
enough to up everything I'm not
cutting down enough to really affect my
experience at all now of course as you
get seven billion people with that
mindset it becomes a different story but
distributed lis they're all thinking
about their own action and that if if I
cut this tree down I have $10,000 worth
of 2x4 s in my pocket and I need to feed
my family and I don't have any
measurably less oxygen but multiply that
by seven billion and we all die right
but if I don't cut this tree down that
tree in the Commons is worth nothing to
me in terms of differential or
competitive advantage and I have a
system where pre something like basic
income even before competitive advantage
I just need to live right so if I can
take something out of the Commons to
live like I'm gonna do that
so gold or diamonds or whatever are
worth a lot because they were perceived
as scarce when we started the valuation
schema and if there wasn't enough for
everyone to have lots of it then some
people could have it and others wouldn't
and those who had it had something that
was unique where they had some
differential advantage but it's still
Fiat right like whether it's just
printed dollars or gold that we ascribe
that value to that is not based on that
the actual material value of the golden
and we set it in bats it's still like
it's a value metric that we made up and
so we'll have gold worth you know
however much per ounce and because of
that if there's gold under some trees
we'll cut down a lot of trees to get the
gold out and burn up the oxygen or
damage it in the process because we have
a system that is valuing differential
value not systemic value that's if you
start saying well how do we actually
advance systemic value and you can't
really tokenize that because as long as
there are separate balance sheets and I
have some number of tokens and I'm
trying to advance the number of tokens
that I have in competition with other
members we're gonna keep getting all
these win-lose dynamics right so the
post capitalist move is a deeper move
than that now does that mean that tokens
and blockchain can't serve a
transitionary role no of course they can
right now
we make up the currency units you know
through a central bank well you can have
another group make up a different kind
of unit and you can build some better
structures into that unit and that can
be valuable
totally
but as long as we still have private
ownership of those units that if I have
more of the units to begin with it's
easier to get more of them if I have
less to begin with it's harder to get
more of them so I have widening wealth
caps built in all of the other shitty
aspects of capitalism all of the
derivatives and complex financial
instruments and up markets will
end up arising from those competitive
structures those are just basically
inexorable ways to game the game so then
our so what do we do we do need a
completely new economics we do need a
completely new system of sense-making we
do need a completely new system of
choice making right governance add an
axiomatically redesigned level and you
know when most people when you ask them
what is economics they think well it's a
system of trade system of barter right
they're already assuming private
ownership and trade and barter that is
then mediated by some kind of currency
but you have systems that don't have
private ownership that don't have trade
right because I don't own to trade
to you we have some kind of systemic
value we just didn't like those ones
because for the most part we thought of
those as communist socialist systems
where if I didn't privately own stuff
then the state was giving me what I
needed but then the state was also
forcing me to do
because as long as there are shitty jobs
that nobody wants to do that we don't
have intrinsic motive to do but the
society needs done how do you get the
people to do the shitty jobs well if we
kind of meet everyone this needs
throughout this thing called like a
state then the state has to force some
people to do the shitty job so we call
that imperialism and we don't like
communism because it's imperialists so
we say well let's let the free market
force them which is if they can't be
smarter and educate themselves better to
do a better job then they get the shitty
jobs and if they don't the state isn't
forcing them but they will still be
homeless and starved it's just where do
we where do we switch the imperialism
right we switch it from the state to the
to the market but we're basically we
still have to have a system of extrinsic
incentive to control people to do
that they're not intrinsically oriented
to do well okay so that's been part of
what we've had to work with and Marx had
thoughts on it and Smith had its
thoughts on it but technological
unemployment is
changing that whole story where
you can start to automate the shittiest
jobs so you can have a system where the
things that people actually could have
intrinsic incentive to do or what are
there for humans to do the things that
you had to extrinsic lis incent them for
you don't have to like that's a new
thing that means an axiom which is how
do we deal with the labor force an axiom
is changing and so we have to go back
and rethink all of our economic ideas
and with regard to sense making there's
a lot of core things that are changing
in terms of our capacity for cents
making you know we have the ability to
have IOT sensors right Internet of
Things sensors that are giving us
real-time data about air chemistry and
water chemistry and soil chemistry and
Fisheries in the Commons and etc and we
have deep learning systems that can be
synthesizing that information we like we
never had sense-making systems like that
like we didn't even have the
technological capacity for things like
that and choice-making systems so
basically we are at the face of deeper
issues and we've ever been at the face
of before but also with deeper
capacities so the same increased
technological capacity that if we keep
using it to take complex things and make
them simple simple or complicated
instead of complex and we keep using it
to fight against each other and win in
competitive win lose games if we keep
doing that with these increased
technologies that's existential but if
we use those technologies to actually
obsolete those core social structures
and create coherency based social
structures where that technology can be
used for not against then I mean we
really do have a fork between radically
better than anything we've ever
experienced or catastrophic well so now
my question is we talked about all these
different structures that we can create
for humanity to exist within but there's
also human nature and not just human
nature but the nature of something being
alive as essentially being a replicator
machine so we have some sort of
intrinsic tendencies that may be very
difficult to hack and no matter how you
structure the system we're going to
default to those tendencies for example
you know that's probably one of the
reasons why communism didn't work it
just in some ways it probably went
against human nature or the nature of
just a lot of things that are alive so
how do we deal with that in your opinion
that's not why communism didn't work
though yes there were things about the
way it was structured that did not
structure themselves well with humans
but it's important to get that it wasn't
like it wasn't a good structure and
up human nature was the problem
if that it actually wasn't a good
structure there were good parts of it
but in trying to keep us from having
economic inequality because economic
inequality would continue to inexorably
widen it became a
lowest-common-denominator system and it
became a system of lack of freedom and
some really key ways so yes it was
against our nature it was actually
against good parts of our nature so then
the question is are there shitty parts
of our nature or inexorably problematic
parts of our nature this will be the
hardest part of the conversation so far
because I'm going to say that what we
call human nature is mostly human
conditioning that is actually quite
changeable and I don't even mean genetic
engineering or brain computer interface
are necessary let's unpack this this the
question you asked is an essential
question when we look at Japan or
Denmark or I think there's a few Nordic
countries that have had decreasing
populations after they reach a certain
level of economics in education it is
not that the nature is to do exponential
population curves forever it that is the
nature within a certain set of
conditions when the conditions change
many of the deepest like even
procreation behavioral dynamics and
drive start to shift without externally
imposed things like birth caps at China
had it's really important to see that
when you look at some of the indigenous
cultures pre capitalism that didn't have
private ownership they had shared
structures and they had languages that
express that concept of sharing they had
radically de-emphasized words like mine
and radically increased words like ours
in any of those cultures we can see some
of that in some of the Fijian Polynesian
cultures the mas wah you know number of
them wherever the mine language was
less emphasizing the nature of the
language also words like selfish and
greedy and jealous were less emphasized
because those are the results of memetic
structures of scarcity based value in a
competitive framework structures so when
we say what is human nature it does a
little bit that's definitely human
nature like an impulse to write oneself
when they start falling or to pull away
from hot right like of these autonomic
functions those are nature but so like
when you say we would get what is
essentially human nature what was
uniquely adaptive about us is that our
genetic selected for memetics right our
genetic selected for a creature that
could continue evolving itself
developing itself within the course of
its life pretty radically which is why a
baby horse can be up and walking in
minutes and it takes us a year think
about how many multiples of the twenty
minutes it takes a horse to get up go
into a year for a human how useless we
are for so long even a baby gorilla can
hold onto its mom's first she moves
around to the trees in the first day we
can't even move our head for three
months right and that's because we're
born jnanis were born basically still
embryos we're we're imprinting the world
were born into because as complex tool
makers and tool evolvers with our
capacity for abstraction we evolved the
environment around us radically and so
creatures they evolved genetically to
their environmental niche but we're
changing our own environment so we have
to be able to adapt to new environments
that we create so we have to come in not
hardwired because it was super adaptive
to be able to throw a spear at one point
but today like you and me don't throw
Spears that much we text and we do other
so we need to not just have really
good genetic orientation for spear throw
and we need to have the capacity to come
here with almost nothing not even move
our head and imprint the world that
we're in and so that memetics is
mediated largely through neuroplasticity
and the ability to have a lot of our
behavior not just bottom-up genetically
controlled but talk-down regulated and
the top-down systems are highly
influenceable and so we can say humans
genetic selected for plasticity and
plasticity has a pretty huge amount of
variance in its capability and so you
know we can create an environment
like in you know look at the child
shoulder situations in Sudan or places
like that where we can take almost
everyone through a process that makes
various degrees of psychopathy we can
also you know like look at Buddhist
culture where you had millions of people
all care about insects enough to not
harm them right beyond the Dunbar number
they had a something that developed
abstract empathy across the population
and so that doesn't mean humans are
naturally psychopaths or naturally
highly empathetic it means we are
naturally capable of being conditioned
in either of those ways or any of many
different ways we do have an innate
impulse towards agency towards
self-actualization within a win-lose
game structure that will look like a
competitive impulse but within other
structures and win-win structures that
will look like the desire to go beyond
my own previous capacity but not to
necessarily be better than or you know
consume somebody or something else and
so that's where there is an innate
impulse but that expresses itself
through context no let's take the next
step there's another really key step
here until very recently humans didn't
have any concept of what evolution was
and we only recently did and we're only
right now beginning to have a deep sense
of what it actually is not just biologic
natural selection but the process by
which subatomic particles come into
atoms come into molecules come into more
complex organic structures the dust
clouds turn into stars and spiral
galaxies that there is that evolution is
this process of increasing orderly
complexity in a way that has more and
more synergy so more and more emergent
property and the emergent properties
define the arrow of evolution and as
we're starting to understand this you
know like very few people but the
beginning of us starting to understand
this we can actually become conscious
agents of evolution we can like I say
holy universe's actually doing
something it's actually moving in this
direction of increasing orderly
complexity we can consciously
participate with that and we move from
just being a part of the whole where
evolution is just kind of this
unconscious algorithmic process so
thinking about feeling about identifying
with and being an agent for the whole
and so then evolution itself becomes an
identically mediated process like we
actually say the whole evolutionary
process resulted in me I am the result
of this whole evolutionary process - in
a way the evolutionary process is kind
of awoke to itself in me as I'm
contemplating it and so then we stopped
needing pushed by evolutionary pressure
and pain to evolve and we start being
able to evolve consciously by what tear
- are down called the lure of becoming
because we actually identify as
evolutionary's right as as part of the
evolutionary impulse and in doing so
really obsolete the need for pain as an
evolutionary driver so I know I said a
number of things in there but human
nature has the capacity to transcend
much of what human behavior has been so
far so well said it's like we're the
tentacles of the universe or something
yeah the sensors and the actuators right
yeah it's a quite a spiritual
proposition to that we are becoming
conscious of what we are and acting
based on that realization yeah and I
actually don't think anything less than
that is adequate for preventing
existential risk and that's a big deal
that really frames up what we're here to
talk about which is as we have
increasingly distributed exponential
ability for impact we really have to
have exponentially increasing good
choice making Omni considerate choice
making everywhere so as long as I when
we talk about wind Lou's game theory at
the deepest level it starts with me
having a sense of self that's separate
from everything else even all the way
down to the semiotic stew the language
right I was told when I was a little kid
I'm Daniel and your mic and your UV and
that's a chair and that's a house and
that's a crow and but it's all this just
separate stuff in universe and I can be
a good boy or a bad boy independent of
what's happening for anybody or anything
else I can actually win at the expense
of someone else losing and a baseball
game whatever and get a whole lot of
praise and someone else winning can mean
that I lost right like I I am NOT on
separate self but I am also a separate
self in competition for the scarce
things including scarce love right and
scarce attention so that's imprinted
that's the basis of the win-lose
structures at the level of individual
separate self-identity when the reality
is we go a little bit deeper if we
weren't playing silly games right what
the am i without all the plants
that make all the oxygen I don't exist I
can't breathe my mother wouldn't have
been able to breathe I wouldn't have
been born right without plants I am not
even a concept so how am i a separate
self if I am required the plants but the
plants required the pollinators and the
micro resi and the soil and on and on
and what would I be without gravity
I'm not anything without gravity
or without electromagnetism what would I
be without the people that came before
me that made the language within which I
think all of my thoughts that has
actually patterned the way in which I
think and feel and structure the world
right and I start to say well I'm
actually I wouldn't exist without all of
it so that South African sang on Ubuntu
I am because we are is actually profound
meaning me as a separate self right okay
so take gravity away take
electromagnetism away take the plants
away I'm floating in the middle of a
universe with no I'm not even floating
there's nothing holding me together
right like the concept of me as a
separate self is nonsense it's a
misnomer really it's just like when you
take the tree out of the rain forest and
turn it into wood it's worth a whole lot
less the context had it was its value
right its value was the content within
the context which co-evolved I am within
a context and without that context I
don't even exist and so when I get that
I am a misnomer as a separate thing that
really I am an emergent property of the
whole I'm an emergent property of the
biosphere but not just a biosphere
because without the Sun I wouldn't be
very interesting either and without the
laws of universe I wouldn't I'm an
emergent property of universe and so are
you and we're interconnected in this and
that's waking up at a cognitive level at
a existential at a spiritual level and
really we need new macroeconomics
economics is basically what do we value
don't value oxygen because we can't get
any competitive advantage off it even
though we'd all die without it but value
the gold because I'll get some
competitive advantage even though I'm
just gonna stick it in a safe not do
anything with it value the whale dead
because I can do stuff with it I don't
value it live right like what do we
value our value system is codified in a
value equation that then determines what
we confer power to that's economics
totally spiritual thing so we need new
macroeconomics that aligns the incentive
of every agent with the well-being of
every other agent and of the Commons
because any gap between your incentive
and my well-being or your incentive and
the well-being of the Commons then you
will do what you're intended to do and
you will externalize harm directly or
indirectly right and with exponential
increasing technology that harm will
always become catastrophic eventually so
we need new macro economics that
fundamentally align our well-beings with
each other and in doing so we have no
incentive for disinformation we only
have incentive for information so now
science becomes science actually right
in journalism actually come to
journalism we can actually make
sense of stuff because I'm not trying to
hide information from you or lead you
down the wrong track so I get there
first and we need you know so like new
macroeconomics new sense make new
systems of choice making all the way
down to a new world view where we
actually identify with the evolutionary
impulse so we don't need pain to push us
we are evolving right we're being and
becoming and doing at the same time for
ourselves and the whole at the same time
and all the way down to our personal
identity shifting from being a separate
self which is just nonsense to being a
unique emergent property of reality and
when I get that you are a unique
emergent property of reality and you
have had life experiences you've sensed
stuff that I haven't you have a
perspective on everything that I
couldn't possibly have you have the
ability to do stuff that I can't do if
you self actualize fully you will create
beauty in the world that I couldn't
write like no amount of Michelangelo's
self-actualization would have done MC
Escher or Salvador Dali like their own
kinds of unique creation
capacity and so
I can only compete with you when we
reduce you and me to very simple metrics
right how much money do we have or how
fast can you run or whatever right but
when we go back to the full metrics and
it's basically an indefinite number of
metrics and the synergistic combinatoric
of those they're incomparable so now the
competition thing is gone because I'm
I'm identified with this whole complex
thing not this little narrow thing that
in that narrow thing we can compete with
each other right when that's gone then
you self actualizing not only doesn't
take away from me you self actualizing
makes a more beautiful universe in a way
that I can't but I want to live in that
more beautiful universe so I'm incentive
to help you self actualize the gist of
the story as I see it is that we awaken
to that to everyone as a unique emergent
property of an interconnected whole who
needs to simultaneously self actualize
help everyone else self actualize with
the attendant economic systems
governance systems etc we're all
individual agentic activity is good for
the individual and the whole
simultaneously just like cells in your
body they're not competing against each
other for scarce resource even though
we've tried to retrofit that shitty
capitalist idea on biology as a weird
kind of confirmation bias they like when
you think of it in almost mythic terms
you have to think of it mythic terms
exponential technology is you know where
does an exponent scale - as we're moving
towards having the power of gods like
Barbara Marx Hubbard said this win you
know she watched the bomb be dropped by
her Godfather's who were you know the
generals that that were directing World
War two and she saw that mushroom cloud
from Hiroshima and she's like none of
the depictions I ever heard of of Zeus's
lightning bolt we're as big as that and
so she went and asked and she asked
Eisenhower
and you know the other generals I think
MacArthur and she said I see this new
power that we have and I see the power
of it that's bad what is the power of it
that's good and they had no answer and
so she set out on that life quest to
answer that question you know but but
this other part of it we can ask is if
we're scaling towards the power of gods
then you have to have the wisdom and the
love of gods were you self-destruct
and so you know when you do you think of
it in those mythic terms it's like
that's really that's really the story
right now and so the other part of that
mythic term is you know the coming of a
different age and an age that is not
categorized or characterized by like
fundamentally separate interest and
competition for scarce resources with
separate interests power over dynamics
but is characterized by this'll sound
corny but characterized fundamentally by
the metric we are optimizing is love
which requires all the complex metrics
of everything the tree is it requires
recontextualizing things and
unobstructed them into their
instantiation rather and why I say love
is what brings the atoms together into
molecules is these attractive forces
right what brings the molecules gether
what prop the two of you together to
make this thing what brought us together
there's these attractive forces that
bring anything together it leads to
synergy that leads to the emergent
properties that leads to evolution and
ultimately we become stewards of that
bringing reality together into higher
and higher order synergies it's funny
how this is such a repeated lesson to go
towards what attracts you instead of
avoiding what repels you like love is
something I've never cared to define as
well as you've to find I'm curious how
you've actually arrived at that being
dimetric like maybe can you unpack that
a little more it's not a metric because
you can't put a number on it so that was
kind of euphemistic language but it is
love is a very besides damaged word
unwell to find word in English but if we
if we want to borrow from another
language and take the eros an agape
model I think it's useful so the eros
model of love erotic love doesn't just
mean sex sex is one place that it
expresses itself but it is a passionate
desire yes you know energy it's an
attraction so we can think of things
being attracted together right people
being attracted together to procreate to
make new life as a special case example
of people being attracted together to
create anything or anything being
attracted together to create anything we
write subatomic particles being
attracted together to have this
relationship that is atom
and so we can think of the evolutionary
impulse right as kind of in eros energy
and the agape energy that's a kind of
love and so when we think about
participating with the evolutionary
impulse of universe consciously
participating with it then we think
about supporting things coming together
in right relationships that are
synergistic right that's what's a mning
at the you know there is no destination
it's an eternal process of becoming and
blossoming the agape love is actually
worth mentioning here it is often
thought of as an unconditional caring
for I think a decent way of thinking
about is you can't love something or
someone meaningfully if you don't
actually see them understand them right
otherwise it's just an abstract kind of
concept but for me to really love you
I've got to understand you have got to
know you which means for me to really
love you have to seek to understand you
and know you and then as I understand
you and know you more I'm able to love
the unique being that you actually are
and in seeing your uniqueness and you're
irreplaceable 'ti in universe I want for
you everything that could help you enjoy
life self actualize contribute fully and
so the process of seeking to see and
know reality and wanting for it and
wanting to add to it is that impulsive
love and I think it's those two impulses
the becoming impulse in the being
impulse the evolving and the nourishing
impulses that become the deepest kind of
drivers of the both inner states and the
macro systems in the future so here's a
difficult question the people who are
creating the economic systems are not
very enlightened at the moment so how
can we and can we help people awaken to
this understanding so that we can create
the kinds of systems that will support
our evolution because we're kind of
running out of time well if you think
about you know within a current economic
system moving up in the ladder of
success in the economic system requires
things like justifying externality the
thing we're doing is really good so it's
worth all
of that mining damage rolled that waste
damage or the the you know port
conditioner workers are in or whatever
so someone whose empathy is really
intact can't do that and so if you don't
have the ability to shut your empathy
off which is kind of low-grade
psychopathy you're just not going to be
able to succeed and as you start to
succeed and get rewarded it's actually a
system that is not just attracting but
incenting and conditioning a kind of
abstract psychopathy and as you get into
financial services even more so because
you are not providing real goods or
services you're basically gain the the
more you can game the system the better
you can do in that dynamic so when you
have a system that attracts in sense and
rewards pathological behavior so it's
important to understand that success in
the current system has required being at
minimum complicit with the the capacity
to and willingness to be complicit with
that system what we think of as power
even which is a power within a win-lose
structure power over is
psychopathological right and so we're
not creating new power structures we're
creating new structures for shared
activity but they won't be power in the
same sense of what we have thought of as
power anymore there's a few aspects of
how people who are in positions of
influence currently can start to to tip
one is as they recognize near-term
existential risks that are inexorably
within the current system which means
they will not win right their attempt to
win where when lose becomes lose-lose
because of the power dynamics exceeding
the playing fields capacity if they
understand that which more and more
people in positions of influence are
starting to then they realize that they
actually need to learn a totally new
kind of game and when they realize that
the new kind of game that is possible
isn't shitty communism it's not like a
lowest common denominator it's a world
where we can create a Commonwealth
economics that has a higher level of
material resource abundance for everyone
than anyone including them currently has
because right now we can't make the best
phone or the best
computer or the best anything
because that science knows how to
because the IP for how to make the best
one is held between ten different
companies that are competing against
each other so we don't get information
coherence we don't even research the
best things in medicine because some of
them aren't profitable so the wealthiest
people today don't have access to good
healthcare because we're not investing
in it the world that they have one end
is ending and that is unavoidable that's
inexorable so that game is not a game
that gets to keep being played in my
what the world that we can create is
better for even the people who are
winning at the current system at the
highest level the world that we can
create we can will have a better system
of medicine a better system of
sense-making a you know a healthier
environment better technological stuff
better transportation because of the
coherence leading to better resource
allocation and development of tech and
etc so we can build a world that is
better for everyone then building our
quality of life today in sustainable
harmony with the biosphere for everybody
the only thing that they would lose is
the differential of how much better it
is for them now than it is for everyone
else
but they can't hold on to that anyways
I've actually seen many people who you
know have been in power positions within
the current system who have been coming
to these awarenesses naturally so that's
an in heartening thing Daniel do you
have any book recommendations for our
listeners if they want to continue
learning about these subjects yeah well
as we were just talking about a game
that's ending in the new game that the
book infinite and finite games by James
Carr says a really great introduction to
thinking about what a world beyond game
theory is and it's short and it's
actually like it is both an interesting
treatise on economics and governance and
social systems and a really profound
spiritual book so I recommend that one
infinite and finite games and you know
books like the collapse of complex
societies by Tainter they go through all
of the you know civilizations of the
past that collapse and how and why they
collapse is a very sobering insight for
people to realize that you know
existential risk and a whole species and
a whole global level we've never faced
before but we have at the level of
civilizations and we almost always fail
and to kind of understand why so that we
can make sure we you're not repeating
that that's actually very valuable very
insightful and if people want to read
you know about existential risk itself
you know going to the future of life
Institute or the Cambridge Center for
the Study of existential risk places
like that and reading their reports
those things have a lot of value going
even back to like limits of growth and
the world 3 model it's surprising how
many places the world 3 model was
accurate from you know when it was
started so there's still value in limits
of growth all of those are good ones if
I had to pick one for people to start
with from here I'd say infinite and
finite games just a good start cool
thank you I'm gonna pick that up any
documentaries or movies or anything
multimedia esque that you can recommend
you know for people who are not already
familiar with Jacque Fresco's work in
The Venus Project they should get
familiar with it because you know there
are elements of what's necessary that
weren't included he didn't the world he
was coming up through he didn't get very
exposed to complex systems theory so the
distinction between needing to build a
world that's complex and self-organizing
rather than complicated was not a clear
distinction and how since making and how
world view happened he was you know
working from a pretty straight kind of
tecnico peon point of view and he
doesn't speak much to the transition of
how we get there but with all those
critiques in place there's a lot that he
spoke to been demonstrated regarding how
you could have a system beyond scarcity
based capital that worked radically
better than this and so I think the
documentaries one is called paradise or
oblivion one's called the choices ours
and also the the second in the zeitgeist
series I Geist addendum the first half
is about fractional reserve banking the
second half is about his work I think
for people who haven't got into post
capitalism and much depth yet looking at
the resource-based economy that The
Venus Project proposed is a really good
entry point to some of the thought
Daniel this has been a fantastic
conversation one of my favorites we've
ever done so thank you again for coming
on and sharing your insights and and
what you've studied this has just been
fantastic for us
yeah very inspirational I'm sure
listeners will love it these were fun
and important topics that we got to
cover today this is
a blast and you know when you ask how
can we help people in positions of
influence shift I think what y'all are
doing is meaningful towards that so I
thank you for that thank you thank you
all right Daniel take care bye that's
all for this episode thank you for
listening for all the books movies and
other things that we mentioned in this
episode go to future thinkers org slash
alright we'll see you in the next
episode bye bye e thanks for listening
to the future thinkers podcast to get
notified of new podcasts and videos go
to future thinkers org and subscribe to
our mailing list you can also find us on
iTunes stitcher and you tube if you like
what we do and you want to help us make
more podcasts and videos give us a like
or you share it with your friends and
consider becoming a patron go to
patreon.com/crashcourse inori org slash
bap last but not least if you want to
get access to more content hidden
episodes or if you just want to chat
with us in previous guests then check
out our community at community future
thinkers org
[Music]
you